Hello and welcome to this lecture.
And in this lecture we will have a brief overview about Django.
So what exactly is Django so to understand Django.
Let's take an example of a social networking website.
So let's say if you want to access a social networking website like Facebook.
So what you essentially do is that you open up your browser and you send a request to the browser for
example you open up the browser you type in some you are like Facebook dot com slash the user name.
So let's say for example you want to extract the information of a user from a social media Web site.
If you want to access information of a particular user you type in facebook dot com slash the name of
that particular user.
So you type this thing in into your browser and what your browser does is that the browser takes this
you are a request and it sends it to the so what.
So this right here is let's assume Facebook server.
So now the job of the server is to take your request.
It's going to read your request and depending upon what data you have requested it's going to look at
that data and then it's going to find a data of User 1.
And it's going to send back a response.
So this response is going to be nothing but the profile of that particular user.
So for example let's say if you type in facebook dot com slash your user name you will get your user
profile.
So this is the entire process which happens when you request for a particular web page from a server.
So this entire thing is nothing but what happens when you access any kind of Web site on the Internet.
So what essentially happens is that you type in a you URL in your browser.
And now that browser is actually going to send that you are all to the specific server and request back
some data.
Now the server was are programmed in such a way that they can handle your request and return an appropriate
response.
So this is exactly what happened here.
But now the main question is how exactly does this particular server know which kind of page or what
kind of data it needs to return back to the browser.
So the server actually knows this stuff because the SO is actually programmed to handle these client
requests and send back appropriate response.
Now how exactly can we program these so was.
So that's where Django comes into picture.
So what exactly is Django.
Django is a free and open source Web application framework.
So whenever you want to build a web application we use Django and Django is nothing but a framework
and a framework is nothing but a collection of multiple components which we can use to build a web application.
So as I earlier mentioned a framework is nothing but a collection of components which allows us to build
sites faster.
So as I earlier mentioned we need to program so was and which angle we can do exactly the same.
So Django is called as a backend framework because Django is used for programming the so was and not
at the front end.
So this is the very specific reason why we call Django as a pack and framework because it is used to
program the backend that is the server was now Django also has an automatic admin interface which supports
crud.
Now if you build any kind of a website so let's say for example you're building an e-commerce Web site.
So for that very specific site you also need to build an admin panel as well.
So for example there is going to be an admin which is nothing but the main person who is going to handle
that entire site and that admin should be allowed to create read update and delete all the data from
this site.
So for that very purpose you need to provide an admin panel for a particular Web site.
But with Django Django actually has a feature which provides an automatic admin interface so that you
don't have to design it from scratch.
So this is one of the features of Django which we are going to look into.
So that was a brief introduction about what exactly Django is.
So the only thing which you need to keep in mind for now is that Django is used for programming the
so was so that they can return an appropriate response back to the client and Django is nothing but
a framework which is a back end framework and a framework is nothing but a collection of components.
So a framework is nothing but it's essentially a bunch of code which we can reuse to build sites faster.
So without wasting any time in the upcoming lecture we will start building over application with Django.